<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>NetBeans QuickStart Guide</title>
	</properties>
	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java, netbeans" />
	<body>
		<section name="NetBeans QuickStart Guide">
			<p>
				This quickstart is a small guide to get you up and running to start using Wicket
				within minutes. This project is meant to be a starting point for your first project.
				If you are looking for examples, please look at the example projects.
			</p>
			<p>
				This document and project assume you have no special plugins or application servers
				installed on your machine. In the
				<a href="#Next_Steps">final section</a>
				of this document some hints are given to speed up your development even further.
			</p>
			<subsection name="Summary">
				<p>
					For the more seasoned developers here's a short list of steps to quickstart your
					Wicket development. All these steps are explained in more detail below.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>download the quickstart project (follow the link in the navigation menu)</li>
					<li>unzip in your projects directory</li>
					<li>rename the directory to the name of your project</li>
					<li>start NetBeans</li>
					<li>create new project with existing sources, point to your directory</li>
					<li>run the Application (right-click on project, choose Run - Application)</li>
					<li>
						open browser to
						<a href="http://localhost:8081/quickstart">
							<code>http://localhost:8081/quickstart</code>
						</a>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					At the
					<a href="#Next_Steps">end of this document</a>
					we suggest some next steps to take.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Setting Up">
			<subsection name="Prerequisites">
				<p>We assume you have the following already installed:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Java SDK 1.4 (or newer)</li>
					<li>NetBeans 4.1 (or newer)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					It is assumed, but not obligatory, that you have installed NetBeans in the
					following (Windows) directory:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<code>C:\NetBeans</code>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Like stated before, it is not obligatory to use these settings, but if your
					installation does not match this one, please substitute your setup for these
					assumptions.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="The QuickStart Project">
				<p>
					Next you need to download the quickstart distribution project from our
					sourceforge site.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						Download the
						<a
							href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=119783&amp;package_id=166850">
							wicket-quickstart distribution
						</a>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Unzip the distribution to the directory where you normally put your NetBeans
					projects.
				</p>
				<p>
					Rename the directory that was just created to your required project name. In the
					following the directory name is renamed to 'foobar'.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Running NetBeans">
			<subsection name="Configuring NetBeans">
				<p>Now it is time to start the NetBeans IDE, if you haven't done so already.</p>
				<ol>
					<li>
						In the IDE, click Ctrl-Shift-N. (Or choose File > New Project.) The New
						Project Wizard appears. Choose Web and then Web Application with Existing
						Sources:
						<img src="images/netbeans-newproject.jpg" />
					</li>
					<li>
						Click Next and browse to the location where you unzipped the Wicket
						QuickStart sources. Select the "foobar" folder (to which we renamed the
						downloaded distribution) for the Location field. Name the project
						"QuickStart". Click Next and Finish.
					</li>
				</ol>
				<p>
					From a traditional NetBeans IDE (or probably any other) perspective, the
					structure of the quickstart project is novel, because the HTML file is located
					within the source package:
				</p>
				<img src="images/netbeans-project.png" />
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Running the Application">
				<p>
					The application has an internal webserver (
					<a href="http://jetty.mortbay.org">Jetty</a>
					) which can be used to quickly develop webapplications. All you need to do is to
					run the application and point your browser to the webserver running from within
					NetBeans.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Right-click the project and choose Run Project</li>
					<li>Start your browser</li>
					<li>
						Point the browser to the local Jetty server:
						<a href="http://localhost:8081/quickstart">
							http://localhost:8081/quickstart
						</a>
						.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Next Steps">
			<p>This section gives some pointers on where to go now.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					take a look at the
					<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net/Examples.html">examples</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					find more information in the
					<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net/manual.html">manual</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					find more information on the
					<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net/wiki">wiki</a>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<subsection name="Jetty Configuration">
				<p>The Jetty configuration file is located in the project directory:</p>
				<blockquote>src/main/resources/jetty-config.xml</blockquote>
				<p>
					Jetty is started on port 8081 in order to avoid conflicts with other installed
					application servers (for instance Tomcat). This way it is easier to test with
					different application servers. This can be configured in the configuration file.
				</p>
				<p>
					See the
					<a href="http://jetty.mortbay.org/jetty/tut/XmlConfiguration.html">
						Jetty documentation
					</a>
					for information on how to configure Jetty.
				</p>
				<p>
					Jetty is started in the
					<code>main</code>
					-method of the
					<code>wicket.quickstart.Start</code>
					class.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Customizing the Application">
				<p>
					The main page definitions can be found in the
					<code>src/main/java/Index.html</code>
					HTML file and the
					<code>src/main/java/wicket.quickstart.Index.java</code>
					class.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Other Application Servers">
				<p>
					Even though this project is aimed at Jetty, it is not prohibited to develop
					using other application servers. If you have another setup, please leave a note
					on how you set up your environment on the
					<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net/wiki">wiki</a>
					.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>