<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>News</title>
	</properties>
	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java, components" />
	<body>
		<section name="News Archive">
			<p>
				Here is an overview of all Wicket related news items posted on our
				<a href="http://wicket-stuff.sourceforge.net/wicket-kickstart">front page</a>
				.
			</p>
			<subsection name="October 30, 2005 - Wicket 1.1 Available">
				<p>
					The Wicket team is proud to announce the availability of Wicket 1.1 for 
					download! Wicket is a Java component oriented web application framework 
					that takes simplicity, separation of concerns and easy of use to a whole 
					new level. Wicket web applications consist of HTML markup and Java 
					classes. No strange languages, no strange markup, no configuration files
					, no specialized, expensive tools: just Java, HTML and you.
				</p>
				<p>
					This Wicket version contains a lot of improvements from the 1.0 version. 
					New features include:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li><b>Simplified feedback and validation</b> - enables custom feedback strategies</li>
					<li><b>Live Component Reference</b> - the examples project contains a component reference showing how to use the components.</li>
					<li><b>JavaScript and CSS support for components</b> - contribute JavaScript and CSS from your component to the using page</li>
					<li><b>Markup Inheritance</b> - enables template pages and components</li>
					<li><b>Inclusion of external markup</b></li>
					<li><b>Simplified Choice component</b> - creating drop down, radio and list components was never this easy</li>
					<li><b>Less dependencies</b> - we removed several library dependencies</li>
					<li><b>Customizable Form handling</b> - easy for quick forms, easily enables full custom form processing</li>
					<li><b>Improved resource handling</b></li>
					<li><b>Date picker component</b> - will not get you dates, but a JavaScript and text field enabled localized calendar component.</li>
					<li><b>Improved URL handling</b></li>
					<li><b>AJAX request handling support</b> - support for two leading AJAX JavaScript libraries is available as separate downloads from our Wicket Stuff project: scriptaculous and DOJO toolkit</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					The Wicket team wishes to extend their gratitude to the user and 
					developer community for their testing efforts and help, making this 
					release a reality!
				</p>
				<p>
					The Wicket 1.1 distribution can be downloaded from the SourceForge servers by 
					following 
					<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=119783">this link</a>.
					The Wicket 1.1 release documentation can be found at: 
					<a href="/wicket-1.1">http://wicket.sourceforge.net/wicket-1.1</a>
				</p>
				<p>
					Thank you for downloading and using Wicket!
				</p>
				<p><i> - the Wicket Team</i></p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="October 19, 2005 - Moved to Wicket home">
				<p>
					The Wicket Quickstart project has been upgraded from the Wicket Stuff project
					and moved to the Wicket core project.
				</p>
				<p>
					In preparation for the Wicket 1.1 release, we have updated the project with regard
					to the following sections:
					<ul>
						<li>
							now includes an <a href="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</a> build.xml 
							file for building your WAR archive using Apache Ant
						</li>
						<li>
							now includes a <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven 1</a> project descriptor 
							for those that want to build their project using Apache Maven (1.0.x and 1.1)
						</li>
						<li>
							now also includes a sysdeo Tomcat plugin configuration file, so you can now run 
							the project directly using the Eclipse tomcat plugin.
						</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Juli 17, 2005 - NetBeans Guide available">
				<p>
					Thanks to the writing talents of 
					<a href="http://blogs.sun.com/geertjan">Geertjan Wielenga</a>
					we now have a full <a href="netbeans.html">NetBeans kickstart</a> description.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Juli 17, 2005 - Wicket 1.0.1 maintenance release available">
				<p>
					The first maintenance release of the 1.0 release of 
					<a href="http://wicket.sf.net">Wicket</a> is available. The Kickstart project
					has been updated to reflect this maintenance release.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		    <subsection name="June 7, 2005 - Wicket 1.0 final Launched!">
		        <p>
		            With the launch of <a href="http://wicket.sf.net/PressRelease1_0.html">Wicket 1.0 final</a>
		            we also upgraded the Wicket Kickstart project to be 1.0 based.
		        </p>
		    </subsection>
			<subsection name="May 4, 2005 - Eclipse Live Demo added">
				<p>
					Using <a href="http://www.debugmode.com/wink/" title="Wink">Wink</a> we have
					put together a live <a href="demos/EclipseDemo.html" target="_new">Eclipse Demo</a>
					showing how to get started developing your first 
					<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net">Wicket</a> application.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="April 18, 2005 - Netbeans guide added">
				<p>
					Finally we have a Netbeans guide for running the kick start project in Netbeans.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="April 15, 2005 - QuickStart has moved">
				<p>
					The project formerly known as 'Wicket QuickStart' has moved into the Wicket Stuff
					project and has been renamed to 'Wicket Kick Start'.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>