<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Wicket 1.0 Announcement</title>
	</properties>

	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java" />

	<body>
		<section name="Wicket Development Team Announces Launch of Wicket 1.0">
		<subsection name="Open Source, component-oriented Java web framework seeks to ease and simplify development.">
			<p>
				<strong>June 7, 2005 -</strong>
				The <a href="/team-list.html" title="Wicket development team">Wicket development team</a>, responsible
				for the open source development of the Wicket Java web framework
				(<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net" title="Wicket">http://wicket.sourceforge.net</a>) under the
				Apache Software License, today announced the launch of Wicket 1.0. Wicket reduces the complexity of 
				Java web development under current frameworks and allows both web designers and Java developers to 
				work with unprecedented ease and productivity, and without expensive, specialized development tools
				or vendor lock-in.  Beyond making web application development easy, Wicket enables developers to 
				create and package advanced, reusable web components without hassle.
			</p>
			<p>
				Wicket splits the problem of creating dynamic web pages into two separate, well-defined portions.
				This division allows coders and designers more freedom to work in parallel and without stepping on
				each other's toes. The design of web pages in wicket is kept in ordinary XHTML web pages which can
				be edited with standard web development tools such as Macromedia Dreamweaver or Adobe GoLive.
				These pages are then made dynamic in an object-oriented fashion by associating components coded 
				in Java. Wicket components are extensible within the Java language much like Swing components and
				can be backed by POJO (Plain Old Java Object) model objects that can be persisted using an ORM tool
				such as Hibernate or JDO.
			</p>
			<p>
				"Wicket development is so much easier. We don't have to explain all configuration files used in our
				previous MVC framework, or how the Velocity language works to new project members. It's you, the Java
				and the HTML.", Martijn Dashorst said when asked why he switched and started helping Wicket development.
			</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="About Wicket and the Wicket Development Team">
			<p>
				The Wicket development team 
				(<a href="http://wicket.sourceforge.net/team-list.html" title="Wicket Development Team">http://wicket.sourceforge.net/team-list.html</a>)
				is responsible for the Wicket open source project. Wicket was originally created by Jonathan
				Locke in the Spring of 2004. Many important improvements and changes have been made since that time 
				thanks to the 6 additional developers that have joined the project: Martijn Dashorst, Eelco Hillenius,
				Chris Turner, Juergen Donnerstag, Johan Compagner and Gwyn Evans.				
			</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Contact Information">
			<p>
				<strong>Wicket Development Team</strong>
			</p>
			<p>
				Jonathan Locke, jonl@muppetlabs.com
			</p>
		</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
