<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>The Wicket Vision</title>
  </properties>

  <meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java"/>

<body>
<section name="The Wicket Vision">
<p><author>Jonathan Locke</author></p>
<p>
    <b>This document was contributed by the original developer
       halfway september 2004. It does *not* necesarily display the current state
       of the project!
    </b>
</p>
<p>
Even though Wicket has just barely been born and is nowhere near maturity 
(or even stability), I am moving on from the Wicket project to pursue other 
opportunities, and so I will not be available to work or comment on Wicket 
in the future.  So this document then serves to:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Explain the overall Wicket vision</li>
<li>Record the motivations behind various design decisions</li>
<li>Set down any ideas I have about future directions</li>
<li>Detail existing issues that need to be resolved</li>
</ul>
<p>
This document assumes that you have familiarity with Wicket and have read
the Wicket User's Guide.
</p>
</section>

<section name="The Overall Wicket Vision">
<p>
What I like about Wicket is that it shows restraint in providing a powerful 
solution to a very specific problem:
</p>
<blockquote>
  enabling abstract, fully component-oriented, programmatic manipulation of markup
</blockquote>
<p>
I once heard Josh Bloch talk about the <em>power to weight ratio</em> of an API.  
The highest compliment anyone could make of Wicket would be to suggest that 
Wicket has a lot of power and not much conceptual surface area.  That is 
the primary guiding principle of Wicket's design and the ideal I would like
to see it approach.
</p>
<p>
In art, negative space is the part that's not the subject.  In music, negative 
space is the rest.  In software, negative space is all the code that you managed 
to avoid writing.  In all three disciplines, it's what separates what is truly
excellent from what is merely good.
</p>
<p>
Following this metaphor, if Wicket is our foreground object, it is defined 
<em>in a negative sense</em> by all the things that it <em>is not</em> (by the background).  
</p>
<p>
In other words, ideally, Wicket is a web UI framework that delegates as many 
areas of responsibility as possible to other, more focused tools and techniques.  
It recognizes that hibernate is good at persistence; that OGNL is good at string 
formatting; that Java properties files are good for localization; that sub-
classing is good for creating component types; that dreamweaver is good at 
doing HTML layout; that Beans are good for structuring properties; and so on.  
</p>
<p>
The more ways that Wicket can find to offload responsibilities (both now and 
in the future), the less it will be.  And thus, the more it will be.
</p>
<p>
The trick for the lead(s) moving forward with Wicket will be balancing all the 
day-to-day needs people are going to be bringing up with this overall vision 
of minimalism.  There ultimately will be compromises.  The "trick" to making 
the right compromises is simply to agonize over all the options for a long time 
and then to only make the compromises that everyone agrees are really essential 
to what wicket needs to be and do.  
</p>
<p>
A big part of this process of agonizing is to act like doctors and "first, do 
no harm".  If localization issues, for example, aren't sitting well with everyone 
yet, there's probably a reason for that.  So, maybe the near-term solution is 
to simply do nothing and let people use the existing the Label component in 
tandem with the existing string resource loading features until any limits to 
that approach (as well as competing ideas) are better understood.  
</p>
<p>
It's easy to add features.  It's often impossible to change or remove them. 
</p>
<p>
Given this, one really good approach to the overall problem of how to evolve 
Wicket while keeping its power to weight ratio as high as possible would be to 
partition off controversial new ideas in a "contrib" package until they are 
broadly accepted.  This way people can experiment and code away and check in 
lots of stuff without affecting the main codebase with untested ideas.  Then, 
when ideas in contrib pan out to everyone's satisfaction, the lead(s) of the 
project could move them into the main wicket packages.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Design Decision Q&amp;A">

<subsection name="Q: What design decisions were made regarding state management?">
<p>
A: One of the primary objectives was to make state management a Java thing 
   that is abstracted away from implementation details like HttpSession.
   In Wicket, state is stored in components that are nested in Pages which
   are all contained in a map in the user's session.  All of this is very 
   well defined and occurs "behind the scenes".  Such a style of coding
   may be unfamiliar to people with experience using existing frameworks.
   Typically Wicket code involves good OO design, use of nested and anonymous
   classes and an overall awareness of components and their models as being 
   the repositories of all state.  It will take time to adapt to this and
   for people to set aside old functional models of programming where they
   accomplish everything with query parameters, session state or their 
   equivalent.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Q: How does Wicket handle stale data and the back button?">
<p>
A: Because Wicket has a first class component object model where the state
   for every page and nested component is available in the user's session,
   it can trace through all that state when model information changes looking
   for pages containing components with models that have changed in ways that
   invalidate earlier renderings of those components and pages.  
</p>
<p>
   This provides automatic handling for the back button, which has to do with 
   stale <em>markup</em>, and can generally be divorced from the typical problems of 
   stale data in a multi-user environment, which should be handled with the
   usual (optimistic) locking techniques in the persistence layer.
</p>
<p>   
   A good example of stale markup is this: If a table on a page is rendered 
   when there are 20 rows in the table's model, a subsequent deletion of a 
   row will invalidate the rendering of the table that is still cached in 
   the user's browser.  When the user accesses the 20th row in the cached 
   page by using their back button, the link will not be backed correctly.
   What's more, a deletion of the first row means that all 19 rows are off 
   by one in terms of the model they reference.
</p>
<p>   
   In Wicket, stale markup caused by deleting a row in a table is automatically
   handled by using the well-controlled server side state which exists in the
   user's session.  If you look at the Cell class you will see this implementation
   (roughly) of the removeLink method (which returns a Link that will remove
   any given cell from its containing table).
</p>
<source><![CDATA[  
    /**
     * Returns a link that will remove this cell from the table that holds it.
     * @param componentName Name of remove link component to create
     * @return The link component
     */
    public Link removeLink(final String componentName)
    {
        return new Link(componentName)
        {
            public void linkClicked(final RequestCycle cycle)
            {
                // Remove cell and invalidate table
                table.getList().remove(index);
                table.invalidateModel();
            }
        };
    }]]>
</source>
<p>
   Notice that once the remove link changes its table's model by removing the
   cell's model from the table list, it calls <tt>table.invalidateModel()</tt>.  This
   method is implemented by Table, which inherits most of the functionality 
   from Component.  If you look at the implementation of invalidateModel in 
   Component, you will find that it looks through every component on every page
   in the user's session.  Any page containing a component using the same model
   is a stale markup rendering and is made stale with a call to setStale.  When
   a user uses their back button to access the stale page at a later time, they
   will receive an appropriate warning.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name='Q: Why Wicket?  And what does "voicetribe" mean?'>
<p>
A: VoiceTribe was the name of the company I was founding with a friend when I
   got so distracted by the ugly state of web frameworks that I decided to write 
   Wicket over the course of about 2 months of intensive effort.  
</p>
<p>   
   The name "wicket" was at first selected simply because it was unique, memorable 
   and easy to say... and yet not used by a serious software project (the owner 
   of the "dodgy IRC bot" called "wicket" which shows up in a Google search was 
   kind enough to give his blessings to me via email to use the name).  It is 
   surprisingly hard to find <em>any</em> short word that is not already used as the 
   name of some software project or other!
</p>
<p>   
   Although the name was selected for no particular reason, there are a couple
   of interesting coincidences.  For one thing, web frameworks have been somewhat 
   of a "sticky wicket".  For another, "wicket" sounds a bit like "wiki" which 
   is Hawaiian for "quick" (you could even think of the name as "wik" "it" ;-)).  
   And finally, the original meaning of wicket was that of a small door.  But,
   especially a small door within a larger door.  I like this image quite a lot.  
   It's modular ;-) and doors represent freedom (from the big J2EE door?).  A 
   picture of a small door within another door might make a nice cover for the 
   User's Guide when it's done.  Either that or a cute little squirrel staring 
   back at the reader through a croquet wicket!
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>    
