<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Home</title>
	</properties>
	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java, quickstart, eclipse, netbeans, intellij, idea" />
	<body>
		<section name="Quick Start">
			<p>
				This quick start is a small guide to get you up and running to start using
				<a href="http://incubator.apache.org/wicket">Wicket</a>
				within minutes. This project is meant to be a starting point for your first project.
				If you are looking for examples, please look at the example projects.
			</p>
			<p>This project has guides to the major three IDE's available:</p>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="eclipse.html">Eclipse</a></li>
				<li><a href="netbeans.html">Netbeans</a></li>
				<li><a href="intellij.html">IntelliJ IDEA</a></li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				These quick start guides assume you have some knowlegde of developing Java web
				applications and using your IDE. This kick start will only give you a working
				environment, it is not intended as a blueprint project.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Incubation">
			<p>
				The Wicket project is an effort undergoing incubation at the Apache Software
				Foundation (ASF), sponsored by the Incubator PMC. Incubation is required of all 
				newly accepted projects until a further review indicates that the 
				infrastructure, communications, and decision making process have stabilized in 
				a manner consistent with other successful ASF projects. While incubation 
				status is not necessarily a reflection of the completeness or stability of the 
				code, it does indicate that the project has yet to be fully endorsed by the 
				ASF.
			</p>
			<p>
				For more information about the incubation status of the Wicket project you
				can go to the following page: 
				<a href="http://incubator.apache.org/projects/wicket.html">http://incubator.apache.org/projects/wicket.html</a>.
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
