<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Buzz</title>
	</properties>

	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java" />

	<body>
		<section name="Buzz">
	
			<p>
			Wicket has appeared in the press in a variety of industry trade magazines,
			including Network World, ComputerWorld, IT World and Information Week.
			Presentations on Wicket have been delivered by Wicket team members at 
			JavaOne in San Francisco and Javapolis in Europe.  The following are quotes
			from reviewers and users of Wicket:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				"I think its an awesome way to deal with this whole web UI framework mess. I am
				happy to see someone take a simple and clean approach to the whole problem, and come
				up with a transparent POJO solution. I like the direction the framework is going...
				Wicket is clean, simple and elegant."
			</p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- Comment on TheServerSide.com</p>
			
			<p>
				"Last week I wrote an article about Wicket and I spent some time discovering and taming 
				it. And I have to confess this: I love it. <i>... snip ...</i> Wicket is 
				not a framework, it's a candy bar. And everybody loves candy bars..."
			</p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- Comment made by <a href="http://weblogs.java.net/blog/gfx">Romain Guy</a></p>
			
			<p>
				The issue that impressed me in the Wicket model is that "Wicket does not mix markup 
				with Java code and adds no special syntax to your markup files." You reference Wicket 
				identities as HTML attributes and define component properties in Java, which allows 
				designers and programmers to work independently (within the obvious constraint of 
				having common goals). There is no need for special tools.
			</p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- From a Network World editorial entitled 
			<a href="http://www.networkworld.com/newsletters/web/2005/0704web1.html">"Nothing Sticky about Wicket"</a>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				In a recent blog post I asked for feedback on what Web frameworks folks are using. Well, I got quite a surprise: Wicket was the most often recommended framework in reader emails!
		    </p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- From an About.com article entitled 
			<a href="http://java.about.com/b/a/194765.htm">
			And the Winner is...Wicket</a>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				"I have used Wicket since last Fall for personal projects. I have 3 kids and a wife so 
				my free-time is very limited. Given that, I had to be very picky about which framework 
				I chose.
			</p>
			<p>
				I've been very impressed with how little hassle it has been to start creating powerful, 
				reusable components and pages with Wicket even under rather severe time constraints.
			</p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- Comment on TheServerSide.com</p>
			
			<p>
				"...after using web MVC frameworks for a couple of years, building ever more complex
				web applications, I moved to component based frameworks. Of these, I think Wicket is
				by far the best..."
			</p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- Comment on Manageability.org</p>
			
			<p>
				"... Talk about a mind blowing experience, it literally took me ten minutes to have a 
				sample application up and running! The Wicket API is very Swing like, which was a 
				welcome change for me, and allowed for a very familiar development experience. There 
				is even an extension that allows for direct use of a Swing TreeModel. There are so many 
				things that I like about this framework ..."
			</p>
			<p class="quoteAttribution">- From a 
				<a href="http://jroller.com/page/wireframe?entry=web_development_done_right">blog item</a> 
				by the Code Poet</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
