<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dedication id="wug.acknowledgements">
	<title> Acknowledgements </title>
	<subtitle>I’d like to thank the Academy…</subtitle>
	<para>Quentin Tarantino reportedly said of Michael Moore’s Fahrenheit 911 
		that it was the first movie ever made to justify an acceptance speech. 
		Although Wicket has been a labor of love and an attempt to demonstrate 
		a better way of doing things, it is likewise an attempt to justify to 
		my colleagues some of the verbal bashings I’ve given to existing 
		presentation layer technologies (JSP in particular). </para>
	<para>While I don’t expect that Wicket will be the be-all, end-all of web 
		frameworks (and probably other people will soon be bashing my framework 
		for its own shortcomings), I hope you’ll agree with me that Wicket is 
		at least a small but significant step forward, and hopefully towards a 
		world where it will be easier and more fun to write web applications. 
		</para>
	<para> Writing Wicket has largely occurred in a vacuum, so there are only a 
		couple of people to thank since hardly anyone has seen it yet. So I 
		will keep this brief. </para>
	<para> Above all, thanks to Miko Matsumura, who encouraged me at every step 
		of the way and provided invaluable feedback on my ideas. Miko is not 
		only one of the very most insightful people I’ve ever met, but also a 
		truly great human being and a treasured friend. I know I’m not alone in 
		thinking so highly of him, as he is probably one of the most highly 
		networked and generally beloved people in Silicon Valley. How else can 
		one feel about an evangelist who once bungee jumped off the bay bridge 
		in a big foam Duke suit (the video is on the web somewhere…)? </para>
	<para> The other person who believed in Wicket from the start was Tim 
		Boudreau. Thanks to Tim for taking time out on his US vacation to look 
		at Wicket and give me much needed feedback. I’ve known Tim since about 
		the 4th grade in rural Western Massachusetts. We discovered computers 
		together through our once-mighty TRS-80 Model IIIs, and he’s always 
		been on the cutting edge of things ever since. Tim and I have a certain 
		camaraderie because we both possess the often frustrating common sense 
		so common among ordinary New Englanders and so rare in large software 
		companies. </para>
	<para> Thanks especially to my mom and my family and to the kind folks at 
		TrafficGauge for supporting my decision to work on this project. </para>
	<para><emphasis>Jonathan W. Locke</emphasis></para>
</dedication>