<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Eclipse Kick Start Guide</title>
	</properties>
	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java, eclipse" />
	<body>
		<section name="Eclipse QuickStart Guide">
			<p>
				This quickstart is a small guide to get you up and running to start using Wicket
				within minutes. This project is meant to be a starting point for your first project.
				If you are looking for examples, please look at the example projects.
			</p>
			<p>
				This document and project assume you have no special plugins or application servers
				installed on your machine. In the
				<a href="#Next_Steps">final section</a>
				of this document some hints are given to speed up your development even further.
			</p>
			<p>
				If you have another IDE you'd like to see quickstart support for,
				don't hesitate to contribute!
			</p>
			<subsection name="Summary">
				<p>
					For the more seasoned developers here's a short list of steps to quickstart your
					Wicket development. All these steps are explained in more detail below.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>download the quickstart project (follow the link in the navigation menu)</li>
					<li>unzip in your workspace</li>
					<li>rename directory to project name</li>
					<li>create new Java project in Eclipse, using previous project name</li>
					<li>run the Start class (Run as - Java application)</li>
					<li>
						open browser to
						<a href="http://localhost:8081/quickstart">
							<code>http://localhost:8081/quickstart</code>
						</a>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					At the
					<a href="#Next_Steps">end of this document</a>
					we suggest some next steps to take.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Setting Up">
			<subsection name="Prerequisites">
				<p>We assume you have the following already installed:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Java 1.4 (or newer)</li>
					<li>Eclipse 3.0 (or newer)</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					It is assumed, but not obligatory, that you have installed eclipse in the
					following (Windows) directory:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<code>C:\eclipse</code>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>and that your workspace resides in the default location:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<code>C:\eclipse\workspace</code>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Like stated before, it is not obligatory to use these settings, but if your
					installation does not match this one, please substitute your setup for these
					assumptions.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="The QuickStart Project">
				<p>
					Next you need to download the quickstart distribution project from our
					sourceforge site.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						Download the
						<a
							href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=119783&amp;package_id=166850">
							wicket-quickstart distribution
						</a>
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					Unzip the distribution into your Eclipse workspace (which is typically located
					under
					<code>C:\eclipse\workspace</code>
					).
				</p>
				<p>
					Rename the directory that was just created to your required project name. In the
					following the directory name is renamed to 'foobar'.
				</p>
				<img src="images/eclipse-rename.png" />
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Running Eclipse">
			<subsection name="Configuring Eclipse">
				<p>
					Now it is time to start Eclipse, if you haven't done so already. Select the
					workspace where you have installed the Wicket quickstart project. In order to
					have Eclipse import your project we will create a new Java project using the
					directory name of your project.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Start the 'New project' wizard in Eclipse.</li>
					<li>
						Select 'Java project' and click next.
						<img src="images/eclipse-newproject.png" />
					</li>
					<li>
						Enter in the 'project name' box the name of your directory (chosen in the
						directory rename action of before). Notice the text at the bottom of the
						dialog saying
						<blockquote>
							The specified external location already exists. If a project is created
							in this location, the wizard will automatically try to detect existing
							sources and class files and configure the classpath appropriately.
						</blockquote>
						<img src="images/eclipse-newproject2.png" />
					</li>
					<li>Leave all other options on their default values and click 'Finish'.</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Running the Application">
				<p>
					The application has an internal webserver (
					<a href="http://jetty.mortbay.org">Jetty</a>
					) which can be used to quickly develop webapplications. All you need to do is to
					run the application and point your browser to the webserver running from within
					Eclipse.
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						Start the Jetty server by right-clicking on the
						<code>src/main/java</code>
						directory in the project and selecting the menu: 'Run as - Java
						application'. If Eclipse prompts you for a main class, browse to the class
						named 'Start'.
					</li>
					<li>Start your browser</li>
					<li>
						Point the browser to the local Jetty server:
						<a href="http://localhost:8081/quickstart">
							http://localhost:8081/quickstart
						</a>
						.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Next Steps">
			<p>This section gives some pointers on where to go now.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					take a look at the
					<a href="/Examples.html">examples</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					find more information in the
					<a href="/manual.html">manual</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					find more information on the
					<a href="/wiki">wiki</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					take a look at the
					<a href="http://jettylauncher.sourceforge.net/">Jetty launcher</a>
					plugin to ease your development
				</li>
			</ul>
			<subsection name="Jetty Configuration">
				<p>The Jetty configuration file is located in the project directory:</p>
				<blockquote>src/main/resources/jetty-config.xml</blockquote>
				<p>
					Jetty is started on port 8081 in order to avoid conflicts with other installed
					application servers (for instance Tomcat). This way it is easier to test with
					different application servers. This can be configured in the configuration file.
				</p>
				<p>
					See the
					<a href="http://jetty.mortbay.org/jetty/tut/XmlConfiguration.html">
						Jetty documentation
					</a>
					for information on how to configure Jetty.
				</p>
				<p>
					Jetty is started in the
					<code>main</code>
					-method of the
					<code>wicket.quickstart.Start</code>
					class.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Customizing the Application">
				<p>
					The main page definitions can be found in the
					<code>src/main/java/Index.html</code>
					HTML file and the
					<code>src/main/java/wicket.quickstart.Index.java</code>
					class.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Other Application Servers">
				<p>
					Even though this project is aimed at Jetty, it is not prohibited to develop
					using other application servers. If you have another setup, please leave a
					note on how you set up your environment on the <a href="/wiki">wiki</a>.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>