<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Wicket changes</title>
    <author email="dashorst at users.sourceforge.net">Martijn Dashorst</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="0.9.15-beta" date="in CVS" description="Last release before march to 1.0">
      <action type="add" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1032507">Create a contrib section (site &amp; cvs) where high level components and other contributions that should not be part of the core can be put.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst">Added quickstart project</action>
      <action type="update" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1087152">Move packages from com.voicetribe.* to wicket.*</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1081709">Replaced the default design of a maven generated website with a more pleasing, non standard look and feel.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1061782">Added Clover logo to front page of our website.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Added support for a configurable character encoding (i18n) for markup files and HTTP response. And added a new example to show how it works.</action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.14-alpha" date="2004-12-06" description="State of CVS">
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Model for PasswordTextField will now be encrypted for persistence (cookie)</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Fixed autoIndex bug. AutoIndex numbers are now unique across a whole page.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Added lots of new and improved Table features. Examples contain displaytag like demos.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">signin example now includes a rememberMe functionality</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Chris Turner">Introduced new ComponentTagAttributeModifier class and associated methods as a direct replacement for HtmlTagModifier and its subclasses.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1072362">Added reset password flag for PasswordTextField in order to support input forms without emptying the contents.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1072080">Implemented multi field validation.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Eelco Hillenius">Implemented support for ui messaging (also used by validation). FeedbackPanel uses this, and is more generic now as well.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Introduced ListView for lists (former Tables) that do not use paging. Table supports paging.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Eelco Hillenius">Fixed bug that resulted in random session timeouts.</action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.13-alpha" date="25-10-2004" description="State of CVS">
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst">Converted confluence documentation to xdocs.</action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
