<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Wicket changes</title>
    <author email="dashorst at users.sourceforge.net">Martijn Dashorst</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="0.9.18-beta (not yet released)" date="TBD" description="Still more refactorings, documentation upgrades and bug fixes">
      <action type="remove" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
		Removed IModel constructors throughout the project and added instanceof 
		logic to Component to wrap model objects unless they are already IModel 
		implementors.  Updated documentation to reflect this.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Implemented getModelLock() method on Component so that client code can 
      	synchronize updates to the model for a component.  Updated core code
      	so that it synchronizes on the returned lock object (which is currently
      	the model's object as returned by IModel.getObject()) during rendering
      	and form model updating.  This lack of synchronization was a bug in the
      	guestbook application which never showed symptoms simply because it had 
      	never been used by many users at once.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Reworked examples navigation.  Worked on code for GuestBook and GuestBook2.
      	Provided base classes for future examples to extend (WicketExampleApplication,
      	WicketExamplePage).
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Reworked feedback messages code significantly including the FeedbackMessages 
      	container class.  Removed all the thread-local code and put feedback messages into
      	Page instead.  Added info(), debug(), warning(), error() and fatal() convenience 
      	methods to Component which report messages via the Page's FeedbackMessages container
      	object.      	
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Wrote a new persistence abstraction that is more abstract and free of Cookieness
      	(IValuePersister).  Implemented this interface using browser cookies in the new
      	class CookieValuePersister.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Got rid of ValidationErrorDecorator and other code by doing a major refactor
      	of the form validation package.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Split up ApplicationSettings and ApplicationPages and moved many of the non-settings
      	getters to Application.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Fixed guestbook test and other problems with example tests.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
      	Made examples work from http://localhost:8080 via redirecting.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1113613">
      	Created FAQ page and added an explanation of why so many classes and methods are final
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1091897">
      	Added comments and refactored renderBody to the more illustrative name 
      	renderComponentTagBody.  Also changed names throughout the project to 
      	match this pattern.  Simplified renderComponentTag() by folding in
		stripComponentName() logic and removed the overload of that method which 
		advances the markup stream in addition to rendering the tag.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1092016">
		Closed request to make RawMarkup class public since we do not want to
		expose this implementation detail.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1091288">
		Changed parser to allow single quotes as well as double quotes around 
		attribute values in XML tags.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1106563">
		Fixed bug where popups expire due to removeNewerThan call in HttpRequestCycle.
		Also removed the method itself since it is not used for any other purpose.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1100078">
		Closed RFE to allow custom object properties on ApplicationSettings since
		ApplicationSettings is really only for Wicket configuration.

		To store "global" objects for your application, just put
		regular old Java properties on your Application subclass. 
		If I'm somehow missing your point, please reopen the bug and
		explain why subclassing Application won't provide the
		functionality you need.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="1032465">
		Closed old RFE for license aggregation since we already have the licenses
		available in the licenses folder in the core.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
		Major reworking of converter code.  Folded localized converters into a 
		single set of converters, removing casts to ILocalizable in the process.  
		Implemented converters for all Java primitive types plus Date, Timestamp 
		and String.  Added javadoc documentation for converter API.  Refactored 
		Component, TypeValidator and Session code to use the new converter code 
		and to enable customization through overrides of getConverter(). Wrote
		new tests for converters.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
		Refactored ComponentTagAttributeModifier and changed name to AttributeModifier.
		Made more of this class private and removed inappropriate tests of private API.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
        Renamed IIdList -> IDetachableChoiceList and IdListAdaptor -> DetachableChoiceList 
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke" issue="">
        Renamed IPageLink.getPageClass() -> IPageLink.getPageIdentity()
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.17-beta" date="2005-01-26" description="Major refactorings">
      <action type="update" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1107845">Moved wicket-examples-hangman into the wicket-examples project.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1107802">Hangman gives NPE at startup</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Martijn Dashorst">Made 'maven eclipse:generate-classpath' plugin work with eclipse projects.</action>
      <action type="update" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Changed the component markup to<![CDATA[<wicket:xxxx>]]></action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke">Changed the registration of the servlet in web.xml to
        <code>wicket.protocol.http.WicketServlet</code>
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Refactored
        <code>autolink</code>and
        <code>border</code>to match the<![CDATA[<wicket:xxxx>]]>component markup
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke">Simplified
        <code>IMarkupParser</code>
      </action>
      <action type="update">Javadoc for several components updated.</action>
      <action type="update" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Refactored
        <code>MarkupParser</code>
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke">Refactored and documented:
        <ul>
          <li>wicket</li>
          <li>wicket.model</li>
          <li>wicket.protocol</li>
          <li>wicket.response</li>
          <li>wicket.request</li>
          <li>wicket.util</li>
        </ul>
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="Jonathan Locke"/>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.16-beta" date="2004-12-26" description="Really the last release before march to 1.0">
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Added Spring-framework integration example to Wicket-examples.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Added support for dynamic languages like Groovy. An example has been added to wicket-examples.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1091100" due-to="Gili">Javadoc bug in MultiLineLabel.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1091101" due-to="Gili">Font bug in paragraph.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1091094" due-to="Gili">Quickstart distribution not downloadable</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Martijn Dashorst">Fixed javadoc warning in ApplicationSettings.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1090226" due-to="Alex Chew" due-to-email="alex_chew at users.sourceforge.net">ListChoice Does not Support 'expression' binding</action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.15-beta" date="2004-12-19" description="Last release before march to 1.0">
      <action type="add" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1032507">Create a contrib section (site &amp; cvs) where high level components and other contributions that should not be part of the core can be put.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst">Added quickstart project</action>
      <action type="update" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1087152">Move packages from com.voicetribe.* to wicket.*</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1081709">Replaced the default design of a maven generated website with a more pleasing, non standard look and feel.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1061782">Added Clover logo to front page of our website.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Added support for a configurable character encoding (i18n) for markup files and HTTP response. And added a new example to show how it works.</action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.14-alpha" date="2004-12-06" description="State of CVS">
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Model for PasswordTextField will now be encrypted for persistence (cookie)</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Fixed autoIndex bug. AutoIndex numbers are now unique across a whole page.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Added lots of new and improved Table features. Examples contain displaytag like demos.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">signin example now includes a rememberMe functionality</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Chris Turner">Introduced new ComponentTagAttributeModifier class and associated methods as a direct replacement for HtmlTagModifier and its subclasses.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Martijn Dashorst" issue="1072362">Added reset password flag for PasswordTextField in order to support input forms without emptying the contents.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Eelco Hillenius" issue="1072080">Implemented multi field validation.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Eelco Hillenius">Implemented support for ui messaging (also used by validation). FeedbackPanel uses this, and is more generic now as well.</action>
      <action type="add" dev="Juergen Donnerstag">Introduced ListView for lists (former Tables) that do not use paging. Table supports paging.</action>
      <action type="fix" dev="Eelco Hillenius">Fixed bug that resulted in random session timeouts.</action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.13-alpha" date="25-10-2004" description="State of CVS">
      <action type="add" dev="Martijn Dashorst">Converted confluence documentation to xdocs.</action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
