<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Home</title>
	</properties>
	<meta name="keyword" content="wicket, web, j2ee, java" />
	<body>
		<section name="Welcome to Wicket">
			<p>
				Wicket is a Java web application framework that takes simplicity, separation of
				concerns and ease of development to a whole new level. Wicket pages can be mocked
				up, previewed and later revised using standard WYSIWYG HTML design tools. Dynamic
				content processing and form handling is all handled in Java code using a first-class
				component model backed by POJO data beans that can easily be persisted using your
				favourite technology.
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					Check the
					<a href="Features.html">feature list</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					Read
					<a href="Buzz.html">some Wicket buzz</a>
					or some
					<a href="/Blogs.html">Wicket blogs</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					Find out
					<a href="Introduction.html">why you should use Wicket</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					Check out
					<a href="QuickTour.html">some examples</a>
					and see them in
					<a href="http://www.wicket-library.com/wicket-examples">live action</a>
				</li>
				<li>
					Download
					<a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/wicket/files">Wicket</a>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				Wicket is released under the <a href="license.html">Apache License, Version 2.0</a>.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Latest News">
			<subsection name="August 22, 2005 - Maintenance release Wicket 1.1-beta 3 Available">
				<p>
					Wicket 1.1-beta 3 is available for download and testing. This is a beta release, so
					you may expect some API changes. Most notable features in this release are:
				</p>
				<ul>
				<li>Component developers can now initialize resources when the app starts up</li>
				<li>Added WebSession.getId() and WebRequestCycle.getWebSession()</li>
				<li>Added AbstractReadOnlyModel Issue: 1250030. Thanks to Igor Vaynberg.</li>
				<li>Fixed: AbstractDetachableModel doesn't propogate attach/detach, Thanks to Cameron Braid</li>
				<li>Fixed: Can't have two FeedbackPanels, Thanks to Simon Berriman</li>
				<li>Fixed: FeedbackPanel produces illegal HTML, Thanks to Gili Tzabari</li>
				<li>Fixed: WicketServlet.doGet URI bug, Thanks to Jan Bares</li>
				<li>Fixed: Classloading problems that caused problems loading markup/resources for components that were loaded by another classloader than the current one</li>
				<li>Extended markup inheritance to support panels and borders</li>
				<li>Made a significant reduction in the size of pages, especially big pages</li>
				<li>Refactored feedback completely. The new code is smaller, more powerful and more elegant, but it will break clients.</li>
				<li>Added automatic multiPart support to Form.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					See the complete <a href="changes-report.html#1_1-b3">list of changes here</a>.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="August 22, 2005 - Maintenance release Wicket 1.0.2 Available">
				<p>
					The Wicket development team has released the second maintenance release of the
					Wicket 1.0 branch. This release fixes some bugs, and with that introduces one
					<strong>API breaking change</strong>:
					<ul>
						<li>newChoiceItem does not use object parameter but selects directly from list Issue: 1263892. Thanks to Arjan Zwaan.</li>
						<li>Backport: AbstractDetachableModel doesn't propogate attach/detach Issue: 1253113.</li>
						<li>Backport: serialization bug in LocalizedImageResource</li>
						<li>Backport: possible NullPointerException in DynamicImageResource.getResourceStream()</li>
						<li>Backport: catch if session is saved to disk and reloaded again but locale is changed</li>
						<li>fix for classloading problems that caused problems loading markup/resources for components that were loaded by another classloader than the current one.</li>
						<li>Backport: closed FileOutputStream in wicket.util.file.Files in finally block</li>
					</ul>
					The API change involves the <code>IResourceStreamLocator</code> interface, where the
					<code>locate</code> method now takes a <code>ClassLoader</code> as an extra parameter. 
					Passing in <code>null</code> will use the context classloader.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="August 1, 2005 - Wicket 1.1-beta 2 Available">
				<p>
					Wicket 1.1-beta 2 is available for download and testing. This is a beta release, so
					you may expect some API changes. Most notable features in this release are:
					<ul>
						<li>JavaScript support</li>
						<li>CSS support</li>
						<li>Markup inheritence</li>
						<li>Experimental AJAX support</li>
						<li>Improved URL handling</li>
						<li>Include of external markup</li>
						<li>Simplified Choice component</li>
						<li>Improved Feedback support</li>
						<li>Thread safe validation (bug fix)</li>
						<li>Immediate button support for Forms</li>
						<li>Panel support for TreeView</li>
						<li>Date picker component</li>
						<li>Component reference examples</li>
						<li>Upgrade of the log4j and concurrent dependencies to their latest releases</li>
					</ul>
					Please download this release and give us feedback on how you like these new features. A final 1.1 release will be available around begin september, so we <em>need your feedback!</em>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="July 24, 2005 - Wicket 1.1-beta 1 Avaliable">
				<p>
					Wicket 1.1-beta 1 is available for download and testing. This is a
					beta release, which means that API's might change. Most notable features
					in this release are:
					<ul>
						<li>JavaScript support - components can now contribute their own JavaScript to a page, opening up possibilities for very rich Wicket components.</li>
						<li>CSS support - alongside with the JavaScript support, Wicket allows components to contribute their CSS to a page</li>
						<li>Markup inheritence - Wicket pages were already able to inherit on the Java side, but now it is possible to 'constrain' the markup of sub pages to a certain place in the markup. If you thought that borders were difficult, this will make your life very easy!</li>
						<li>Date picker - as a demonstrator for what you can do with our new JavaScript support, we have included a Date picker component in the <em>wicket extensions</em> package.</li>
						<li>Component reference examples - an ongoing concern: documentation and component reference. We have started building small component examples in the Wicket examples project.</li>
					</ul>
					Please download this release and give us feedback on how you like these new features. A final 1.1 release will be available around begin september, so we <em>need your feedback!</em>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="July 17, 2005 - NetBeans kickstart guide available">
				<p>
					Thanks to the writing talents of Geertjan Wielenga, the
					<a href="http://wicket-stuff.sourceforge.net/wicket-kickstart/index.html">Wicket Kickstart</a>
					project now hosts a guide for kickstarting you Wicket development using
					<a href="http://www.netbeans.org">NetBeans</a>
					. The project has been updated to incorporate the latests Wicket maintenance
					release.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<p>
				See
				<a href="News.html">the news archive</a>
				for more (older) news.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Special Thanks">
			<p>
				The Wicket development team would like to thank the following partners for
				supporting Open Source in general and Wicket in particular.
			</p>
			<a href="http://www.topicus.nl" target="_blank" class="logoLink">
				<img alt="Topicus B.V." src="images/topicus.gif" />
			</a>
			<a href="http://www.yourkit.com" target="_blank" class="logoLink">
				<img alt="YourKit" src="images/yip_logo.gif" />
			</a>
			<a href="http://www.cenqua.com" target="_blank" class="logoLink">
				<img alt="Clover"
					src="http://www.cenqua.com/clover/doc/skin/images/clover_logo.gif" />
			</a>
			<a href="http://www.sourceforge.net" target="_blank" class="logoLink">
				<img alt="SourceForge.net"
					src="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=119783&amp;type=1" />
			</a>
			<p>
				<!-- Begin Nedstat Basic code -->
				<!-- Title: Wicket - Home -->
				<!-- URL: http://wicket.sourceforge.net/ -->
				<script language="JavaScript" type="text/javascript"
					src="http://m1.nedstatbasic.net/basic.js">
				</script>
				<script language="JavaScript" type="text/javascript" src="nedstat.js"></script>
				<noscript>
					<a target="_blank"
						href="http://www.nedstatbasic.net/stats?ADUqkAqz13yUdWzu82RZ+ob42qQg">
						<img src="http://m1.nedstatbasic.net/n?id=ADUqkAqz13yUdWzu82RZ+ob42qQg"
							border="0" width="18" height="18"
							alt="Nedstat Basic - Free web site statistics
Personal homepage website counter" />
					</a>
					<br />
					<a target="_blank" href="http://www.nedstatbasic.net/">Free counter</a>
				</noscript>
				<!-- End Nedstat Basic code -->
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>